Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Rwanda Videotapes Series, 1992-1999, 5 boxes
  - Bloody Tricolour, VHS [TRT 00:43:00] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW011)
    This video explores the extent of France's involvement in Rwanda and the degree to which it can be implicated in the events that lead to the genocide. It also attempts to explain why a European power would take such a strong interest in the affairs of such a small central African nation. The report begins by explaining that President Francois Mitterrand sent French troops into Rwanda, a country it had never colonized in October 1990 following the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) invasion. According to various officials, France wanted to maintain relations with a French-speaking Rwanda and feared the effects of an RPF-influenced government. The video traces the genesis of the RPF back to the refugees who fled Rwanda during the Hutu revolution in the early 1960's. Many of the Tutsi went to Uganda where they learned English and began planning their eventual return to their homeland. The report hypothesizes that the French worried that the United States overly influenced the RPF. The French accused Paul Kagame, the RPF leader, of being little more than a CIA product. Kagame was in fact invited to the states to receive military training. The report then explains that the French qualified the RPF invasion in 1990 as a terrorist act and sent French troops in to evacuate foreign expatriates. However, Panorama learned that among the French deployment there was a strong training contingency, intelligence experts and military advisors. The French maintained a military presence in Rwanda until the signing of the Arusha agreements in 1993. The report reflects on the fact that France provided more aid and development money to Rwanda during the Habyarimana regime than any other European power. However, since the new RPF government has taken power, France has all but abandoned this once favored nation. The report includes numerous interviews with government officials including President Mitterrand's son, Jean-Christophe Mitterrand, Presidential Adviser on African Affairs from 1988 to 1992. Jean Carbonare who lead the International Human Rights Commission mission to Rwanda in 1993 and was President of "Operation Survie" immediately following the genocide, is quoted as saying "I am very critical of my country before, during and after the genocide. There is a great deal of suspicion about the delivery of arms. You can't on one hand give arms to those responsible for genocide and then say we take pity on the Rwandan people, we'll give you humanitarian aid. I think this is a question of consistency. I'm very unhappy, as a Frenchman, to see my country not have that consistency."
  - Nyirabayazana, VHS [TRT 00:52:00 ] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW012)
    Air Date: 1996 July 20
    Producer: BBC Panorama
    "This video shows a historical background to the Rwandan conflict since the colonial time to its 1994 genocide.
    The document looks into the first year of independence, after a description of Habyarimana regime and his political party the Mouvement républicain national pour la démocratie et le développement (MRND). The video describes the militia organization, their training, and sites of genocide. The document shows
    the interim government led by Theodore Sindikubwabo. The reporter in this video accuses this interim government of organizing and carrying out the genocide."
  - Interview with Bagosora in Goma, VHS [TRT 00:49:01] (Box 117, Video-cassette RW013)
    Producer: Reporters Sans Frontières
    In the video Bagosora explain his role in previous government and denies his involvement in death squad killing before and during the genocide. When asked if he could go to the international criminal tribunal and answer questions in relation to the war and his involvement, Bagosora approved the idea of the international tribunal and agreed to stand trial if accused. But he refused to stand trial in Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) court he accused to be judge and jury. Bagosora argued that the security council caused all problems in Rwanda by imposing an arm embargo on the Forces Rwandaises de Défense (FAR) army. Bagosora also accused the international community for conspiracy by collaborating with the Tutsi minority group. Bagosora denies accusation for having said in Arusha that he was going to prepare an apocalypse if the Arusha Peace agreement was going to be implemented.
  - Interview with F. Nahimana in Yaounde, Cameroon, VHS [TRT 02:07:05] (2 copies) (Box 117, Video-cassette RW014)
    "In this tape Nahimana talks about his professional life as an African historian and his role as the director of Radio Télévision Libre des Mille Collines (RTLM).
    In the interview Nahimana denies the accusation that he failed to used his position as the director of RTLM to stop the journalists from broadcasting incitement and hate messages through RTLM radio. Nahimana accuses Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) for trying to discredit him because of his historical research and publication on Rwanda which didn't please the Tutsi community.
  - Rwanda, The Betrayal, VHS [TRT 00:54:00] (Box 117, Video-cassette RW015)
    Air Date: 1996 Sep. 12
    Producer: RTBF-Charleroi, JT
    "A psychological search into the human soul. Lindsey Hilsum had launched a full investigation reaching the core of evil. Her analysis was that the core of Rwanda was rotten and even the church which was supposed to be the "moral authority, the most powerful institution in the land had a rotten center."
    "You haven't yet discovered man, neither in his greatness nor in his misery," Ntezimana, a theologian, told Lindsey Hilsum. His theory was that the missionaries had a historical responsibility. They brought the Christian revelation, which reinforced the traditional attitude of naiveté. It was easy not to question the teachings of churches. Everything the priest said was taken as truth. That behavior was the prelude to genocide. The church in this search for truth was accused of encouraging the evil that took root in the hearts of the Rwandans. Orders were blindly carried out. Many churches are under investigation for their participation in the killings. Some nuns and priests fled to Zaire. Others have adopted the denial attitude, few Catholic leaders spoke out during genocide, and many were helpless witnesses to the carnage.
    Hilsum goes deeply into the problem, questioning herself and her actions during the genocide. Hilsum was present at the time of the massacres and found it hard to help anyone because "she wasn't brave enough, or strong enough to protect them." The important thing is not to pass judgment on the people but to investigate the reason that lead to the madness.
  - Kibuye, International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR) Investigators Video, PAL SECAM [TRT 02:37:07] (3 copies) (Box 117, Video-cassette RW016)
    Air Date: 1999 Sep. 16
    The tape shows the map of Kibuye, then moves to an aerial view of the town for approximately 30 minutes. The rest of the video shows parts of the church where the massacres took place, mass graves sites, a home that housed priests. A few interviews conducted by Dan Gowen, Sara Darehshori, Pierre Heuts and Sjouk Eekmaa, mostly inaudible because of the bad acoustics. The video ends in an aerial view of the trip back to Kigali.
  - Reporteurs Sans Frontières, 1ère cassette, August 1993, PAL SECAM [TRT 04:00] (2 copies) (Box 117, Video-cassette RW017)
    Original Language: French
    The tape contains interviews conducted by Reporteurs Sans Frontières to investigate the allegations that Rwandan Ex-Forces Rwandaises de Défense (FAR) tortured the journalists. The tape focuses on Janvier Africa. Janvier Africa claims to be ex-member of death squad and names all members of the death squad including Captain Simbikangwa. In his interview with Reporteurs Sans Frontières, Capt. Simbikangwa denies all accusations. The tape contains other journalists' interviews discussing their mistreatment and torture by Capt. Simbikangwa and his staff.
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 1 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW017_01.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW017_01.mp4)
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 2 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW017_02.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW017_02.mp4)
  - Reporteurs Sans Frontières, 2ème cassette, August 1993, PAL SECAM [TRT 04:00] (2 copies) (Box 117, Video-cassette RW018)
    Air Date: 1996 Sep. 13
    "The tape contains interviews conducted by Reporteurs Sans Frontières to investigate the Rwandan journalists' torture
    The tape focuses on Janvier Africa. Janvier Africa claims to be ex-member of a death squad and names all the associates in that organization. Captain Simbikangwa denies the accusation that he was a member of the death squad.
    The tape also contains interviews with other journalists who claimed to have been tortured by the secret service agents in Habyarimana government."
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 1 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW018_01.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW018_01.mp4)
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 2 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW018_02.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW018_02.mp4)
  - Reporteurs Sans Frontières, 3ème cassette, August 1993, PAL SECAM [TRT: 01:34:00](2 copies) (Box 117, Video-cassette RW019)
    Air Date: 1996 Sep. 17
    "The tape contains interviews with Gahigi Gaspard. Gaspard explains how Radio Télévision Libre des Mille Collines (RTLM) radio was created. In the interview Gahigi questions the credibility of Janvier Africa in his claims. The same tape contains an interview with Rangira Adrien explaining his work as a freelance journalist for Kanguka.
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 1 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW019_01.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW019_01.mp4)
    - Digital preservation and use files, tape 2 (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW019_02.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW019_02.mp4)
  - Les oubliés de Kigali, VHS [TRT 00:56:39] (Box 117, Video-cassette RW020)
    Producer: Wild Heart Production
    "Who was responsible for the death of the 10 Belgian soldiers? Was it an error of command? Death was not caused by fatality but it occurred out of negligence. Parents, families and most of the Belgians want the truth behind their death. They want to find out who was responsible. It is true that after the president's plane was shot down, the prime suspects
    were the Belgians in the eyes of the Rwandans. Rumors were quickly fed of the Belgian responsibility in shooting down the plane. The ten Belgian soldiers killed were assigned to protect the Prime Minister Agathe Uwilingiyimana. Col. Luc Marcha the commander of the Belgian soldiers was accused of failing to give clear instruction to his soldiers"
  - Unending Exile Erupts: New Conflicts in Rwanda, VHS [TRT 00:09:35] (Box 117, Video-cassette RW021)
    Air Date: 1996 June 18
    Producer: US Committee for Refugees
    This video is based on an investigation of Rwandan refugee camps in Uganda carried out by the U.S. Committee for Refugees. A narrator provides a brief background of Rwanda's colonial history, its ethnic make-up and the events that led to the current conflict between the predominantly Tutsi forces of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and Habyarimana's primarily Hutu regime. The video includes footage from inside the camps and short interview sessions with some of the refugees. It ends with footage of soldiers and a call for negotiations that include participation of the exiled refugees.
  - International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR) Internal Video, Prefecture Kigali, PAL SECAM [TRT 01:28:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW022)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct.25
    "The tape contains a Belgian television report on social and political situation in Rwanda during and after the genocide.
    In the tape, Belgian reporter discusses the killing in Ndera hospital after the Belgian soldiers left the premises. The journalist discusses also the life of street children in Kigali. The tape contains interviews with some Rwandan residents in Belgium. The tape contains also some Belgian government official such as Melchior Watheler discussing the assassination of Belgian soldiers in Rwanda."
  - Rwandan Nightmare, VHS [TRT 00:42:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW023)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct.01
    Producer: Independent Television News Production for Channel Four
    This Rwanda Nightmare is a story of a journey of extremists tearing the country apart, a true account of the numbing horror that was Rwanda in 1994. Does anyone understand what happened in this part of the world? According to Catherine Bond the "agony seemed to the outside world a senseless tribal bloodbath war" that had no impact on the international community and reinforced its lack of responsiveness toward the killings. However, to many observers and experts on this central part of Africa, the legacy of colonialism fueled the conflict and exacerbated the division between Hutu and Tutsi which became the source of tension since the country's independence in 1992. The conviction that the other is the plague, that the only way is the eradication of a no ethnic but just socially and economically different group " If you want to eliminate rats, you have to start with the little ones", or that " Their progeny are the rats of the future" make one wonder who and what reinforced the hatred that became so embedded in the Rwanda culture. The government had its fair share of the blame by using a strategy that that systematically destroyed the bonds of family and friends. By doing so it spread the blame to tens of thousands of Rwandan to alleviate its own guilt.
  - Coalition pour la Défense de la République (CDR) Demonstrations on October 18, 1992, VHS [TRT 01:39:41] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW024)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct.05
    "CDR Demonstrations of October 18th, 1992 condemns Museveni for helping Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and Nsengiyaremye's government
    A few clashes with security on the way to the demonstration site. CDR leaders' speeches in Kinyarwanda focus on negative criticisms. Crowd cheering and singing CDR songs containing propaganda against other political parties."
  - Coalition pour la Défense de la République (CDR)-Mouvement démocratique républicain (MDR) Round Table Meeting, VHS [TRT 01:00:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW025)
    Air Date: 1992 Nov. 2
    Producer: Television Rwandaise
    The tape contains a political debate hosted by the Rwandan journalist Venuste Nshimiyimana. The debate is between Twagiramungu representing MDR and CDR leaders. The debate turns around the CDR's accusation of collaborating with Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and selling out Rwanda.
  - Coalition pour la Défense de la République (CDR) Meeting in Butare, VHS and DVD [TRT 01:41:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW026)
    Air Date: 1992
    This video of a CDR rally in Butare was taken from a hand-held camera, featuring speeches of CDR leaders on the principals and ideology of the CDR. The speakers are cheered by a quite large crowd of members using words such as CDR power.
  - Ntarama Massacre Site, VHS [TRT 00:09:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW027)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct.07
    Synopsis: A short video on Ntarama massacre site. Skulls and skeletons rotting away and being exposed to the human eye. Ntarama was the site one of the most horrible massacre that took place in 1994. The official figure mentions 5000 people gathered and killed in the church. Only few survivors. No sound just images.
    - Digital preservation and use files (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW027.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW027.mp4)
  - Benson Ngarambe, 1995, VHS [TRT 01:23:29] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW028)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct.09
    Several eye-witness from Mugonero in Kibuye are discussing the killing in church. All witnesses claim that Ntakirutimana called Nkuranga, Kajongi, and Sebihe to come out from hiding to join the rest of the Tutsi gathered in church to be killed together. The witnesses are accusing Ntakirutimana and his son of collaborating with the militias under the leadership of Ruzindana. When asked what these witnesses would like to see the international community doing specially the USA, one witness's wish is to bring Ntakirutimana back to his village to let the people look into his eyes and to give to him the opportunity to see that all Tutsi didn't die. All people interviewed in this tape accuse Ntakirutimana of failing to protect them and his son of collaborating with the militias and the government soldiers in the killings. One person in the interview claims having seen Gerard Ntakirutimna carrying a gun and killing people.
  - USCR, Rwanda: Human Atrocities (Raw footage), PAL SECAM [TRT 01:23:41] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW029)
    The video contains views of massacre sites in Kaduha, Mugina. The second part of the video shows views of refugees in camps. The reporter discusses the condition of refugees in camp. The refugee being interviewed discusses the horror they faced before leaving their village.
  - USCR Site Visit to Rwanda, PAL SECAM [TRT 00:11:30] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW030)
    Roger Winter s a freelance reporter accompanied by Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) soldiers and some government officials visited massacre site in Bugesera, the Rwanda and Burundi border, the Rusumo water fall, and many other places in Rwanda. Interviews with local residents are translated by an RPF soldier. Amongst people being interviewed there is a large number of children.
  - International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR) Internal Video, Jan Wilken, PAL SECAM [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW031)
    1. ICTR private investigator, Jan Wilken, filmed local workers hired by Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) soldiers to excavate mass graves near Kabuha in the region of Gikongoro. Scaffolds made of wood have been built and the bones and other remains are piled on to them. The RPF wants these testimonies of the genocide as proof of the horror that took place in 1994. They also want foreign journalists to include these images in their reports so that the whole world can witness the result of the terrible events of 1994. According to an ICTR investigator about 10.000 or more were murdered in and around this site.
    2. We get an aerial view of a church in the region of Kabuha that was site of one of the massacres.
    3. A burial ceremony in Mugina, Gikongoro. They are burying the remains of victims of the genocide that were dug up from some of the mass graves. A speech is addresses to survivors and family members of the murdered. Huge white plastic bags were brought to receive the bodies exhumed from opened mass graves to be reburied properly. The bodies were first lined up in smaller bags before finally being lowered into the ground.
    - Digital preservation and use files (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW031.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW031.mp4)
  - Massacre Along the Road, VHS [TRT 00:06:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW032)
    Original Language: [not available]
    In this scene along the road, Hutu militiamen are killing a group of Tutsi while two women plead for their life. After about fifteen minutes (according to reporters) the women are murdered too. According to a documentary by Anna Der Wee, "The Dead are Still Alive" the scene takes place in Kigali near the old French school.
  - The Dead are Still Alive, PAL SECAM [TRT 00:34:00] (2 copies) (Box 118, Video-cassette RW033)
    Air Date: 1995
    Producer: Wild Heart Production, BRTN - Panorama Belgium
    Original Language: Dutch, Flemish, French/Subtitles: Dutch
    "The documentary begins with Habyarimana's plane crash then moves slowly through the weeks that followed that fatal day which launched the violent response to years of immense tension and social-economic differences between the Tutsi and Hutu.
    Evacuation of foreigners around the 10th of April. Evacuation of a psychiatric center where a number of Rwandans had sought refuge. However, they are not rescued by the Belgian and French convoys sent to evacuate the foreign nationals.
    April 17; Kigali Airport. Preparing to evacuate foreigners.
    April 23; trucks loaded with refugees head for the border.
    April 28; a massive exodus towards the Tanzanian border.
    May 1; life in the Benaco camp.
    May 18; the reporters return to Rwanda. Terror and desolation reign.
    June 9; somewhere in northern Rwanda.
    June 23; the arrival of the first French military contingent as part of Operation Turquoise. Though its intent is as a humanitarian mission there is fear it will become a military intervention and that the French will side with the Hutu.
    July 4; most of Rwanda is now in the hands of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF).
    Jean Kambanda, Prime Minister of the interim government, accuses the RPF of shooting down Habyarimana's plane on April 6, 1994.
    July 18; Goma refugee camp. At the instigation of Hutu elders, young thugs confiscate food delivered by NGOs and the international community. They distribute the food as they see fit.
    A leader of the Interahamwe gives a speech."
  - BBC News on Rwanda, Tape 1, PAL SECAM [TRT 01:33:00] (Box 118, Video-cassette RW034)
    Air Date: 1994
    Original Language: English, Kinyarwanda, French/Voice-over: English
    1. Four weeks of fighting and nearly 1/4 of a million have been killed. The UN is condemned for pulling out.
    2. A history of United Nations intervention in Africa. The first intervention took place in 1960 in the Congo. The latest UN mission in Somalia was highly criticized. The American led force switched from humanitarian in scope to military following the deaths of several American soldiers. The Americans are accused of acting outside the control and command of the UN even though the UN ultimately had to take political responsibility. The operation was characterized by a "total lack of peacekeeping experience."
    3. (1994 May 10) The focus here is the refugee problem on Tanzania's border, problems with water and sanitation. Mixed Tutsi/Hutu couples are running from the problems in Rwanda and living in the same squalid conditions as everyone else in the camps.
    In the wake of failed mediations and negotiations, Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) soldiers have continued advancing towards Kigali.
    The RPF is opposed to foreign countries meddling in the war.
    The UN believes that a peacekeeping force in Rwanda should be composed of African troops. Tanzania is one of the countries expected to participate if African troops are called upon to intervene. The head of the Tanzanian army comes for a visit to the UN headquarters in Kigali. He met with an RPF colonel. The Tanzanian General is unhappy about all the Rwandan corpses littering Tanzanian water sources.
    4. (1994 May 13) The focus is on the Rwanda/Burundi border: the one has descended into hell the other is teetering on the edge of anarchy. Most of the Tutsi in Gitarama are dead; the survivors are merely waiting to die. It is argued that the Hutu were overwhelmed by propaganda from the radio urging them to kill their Tutsi neighbors. There is footage of a village outside of Gitarama. It is difficult to see what the international community could do to make a difference in the face of such horror.
    5. (1994 Aug. 14) Questions are asked about the effectiveness of the UN peacekeeping mission.